<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Coding Interview | Ivan Carvalho</title>
    <link>https://ivaniscoding.github.io/categories/coding-interview/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://ivaniscoding.github.io/categories/coding-interview/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Coding Interview</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 06:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://ivaniscoding.github.io/images/icon_hud7c04f8250daa34436c1572b3b03bb6e_328675_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Coding Interview</title>
      <link>https://ivaniscoding.github.io/categories/coding-interview/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to survive coding interviews with a single line of Python code</title>
      <link>https://ivaniscoding.github.io/posts/codeinterview/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 06:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ivaniscoding.github.io/posts/codeinterview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Entering the world of coding interviews can be daunting. Whether you
are a recent graduate with a bachelor’s or master’s degree in Computer
Science or a senior industry professional, questions may arise with
regards to which programming language to use and which strategy to
follow before and during your coding interview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This guide will give a simple answer out of the many possible one for
that question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To keep things simple, I recommend the Python programming language.
And to keep our strategy even simpler, I recommend writing all your
solutions in a single line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing your code in one line can bring numerous benefits. Firstly,
if there is a bug, you don’t need to worry about which line of code the
error happened. Secondly, one line progams are concise. Combined with
the fact that Python is similar to plain English, this strategy helps
your interviewer understand your solution better. In fact, it is like
reading one very long sentence with many commas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you still stressed about the coding interview and in doubt on how
to code in a single line? You need not worry, because I will provide
examples and tips throughout the rest of this article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;recursion-is-your-friend&#34;&gt;Recursion is your friend&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recursion is a powerful concept that allows us to reutilize code.
Hence, it fits perfectly with Python solutions using one line of
code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s take for example the task of inverting a binary tree (&lt;a
href=&#34;https://leetcode.com/problems/invert-binary-tree/&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;). This
question is rumored to be a frequently asked questions for candidates
that write package managers for macOS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/IvanIsCoding/2bc07fa83e5547f4d541aadb85fd90d9.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the example above, recursion does most of the work. To invert a
binary tree, we swap the left and right nodes and then keep repeating
the process. Clear and concise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conditional-operators-are-helfpul&#34;&gt;Conditional Operators are
helfpul&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This detail was also in the last code snippet, but we can discuss it
individually. Do not waste multiple lines writing &lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code&gt;else&lt;/code&gt; statements! In fact, Python lets you write conditional
operators in a single line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider the following code that computes the depth of a binary tree
(&lt;a
href=&#34;https://leetcode.com/problems/maximum-depth-of-binary-tree&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;)
.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/IvanIsCoding/f9f0f4e313c75513515695fd70a2ff62.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to conditional operators, your code fits concisely in one
line. The &lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;else&lt;/code&gt; statements let you
handle correctly the base case for the recursion which is the empty tree
node.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;lambdas-are-powerful&#34;&gt;Lambdas are powerful&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lambdas, also known as anonymous functions, let us define Python
functions without wasting unnecessary lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take for example the task of finding the first palindrome in a list
(&lt;a
href=&#34;https://leetcode.com/problems/find-first-palindromic-string-in-the-array/&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/IvanIsCoding/de20fcd81807250c6c3e26be1b807b28.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the &lt;code&gt;lambda&lt;/code&gt; statement, we didn’t need to define
a separate function to check for palindromes
(&lt;code&gt;x == x[::-1]&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-walrus-is-a-must&#34;&gt;The Walrus is a must&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I told you about the Walrus and me, man&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know that we’re as close as can be, man&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:right;&#34;&gt;
- The Beatles
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The walrus &lt;del&gt;was Paul&lt;/del&gt; was introduced in &lt;a
href=&#34;https://peps.python.org/pep-0572/&#34;&gt;PEP 572&lt;/a&gt;. Because the
feature landed in Python 3.8, it is higly likely that you can use it as
of 2024. The walrus lets us write less code, which is great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The true power of the walrus, however, appears when it is combined
with lambda functions, because it yields recursive lambdas. Now you
don’t need to waste a separate line to define a recursive function!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take for example the task to check if a binary tree is symmetric (&lt;a
href=&#34;https://leetcode.com/problems/symmetric-tree/&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/IvanIsCoding/c0f65cbd52e496b2bc30f1db12044163.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lambda definition with the walrus operator
(&lt;code&gt;f := lambda&lt;/code&gt;) allows us to define a recursive function that
solves the problem in a single line. The code does not need to waste
lines in superfluous function definitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-standard-library-is-one-function-call-away&#34;&gt;The standard
library is one function call away&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python is known for its included batteries i.e. libraries that ship
with Python. They can be useful for coding interviews as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a misconception that you need your &lt;code&gt;import&lt;/code&gt;
statement in a separate line. But that is not necessary due to the
&lt;code&gt;__import__&lt;/code&gt; function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I demonstrate that in the solution for calculating the majority
element in an array (&lt;a
href=&#34;https://leetcode.com/problems/majority-element&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;) .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/IvanIsCoding/3d275126409348dbbd7ffea256ff848c.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Python has a built-in &lt;code&gt;Counter&lt;/code&gt; class that handles this
exact case. By using the standard library, we reused existing code and
made our solution simpler without having to sacrifice an extra line for
the import.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-wheel-can-be-reinvented&#34;&gt;The wheel can be reinvented&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes your interviewer will explicitly forbid you from using the
standard library. In those cases, it is likely take you can write
similar code still in one line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take for example the task of sorting an array from scratch (&lt;a
href=&#34;https://leetcode.com/problems/sort-an-array/&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;). We can
fit a Randomized Quicksort in one (very long) line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/IvanIsCoding/b95a3999a878e852e31ce1edda498d7b.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the interviewer complains about using &lt;code&gt;random.randint&lt;/code&gt;
though, you can just read from &lt;code&gt;/dev/random&lt;/code&gt; instead. And if
they complain about opening &lt;code&gt;/dev/random&lt;/code&gt; with the Python
built-ins, you can use punched cards to execute code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;believe-in-yourself&#34;&gt;Believe in Yourself&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might find harder questions along your coding interview journey.
Do not panic. Believe in yourself and keep going. Look at the following
solution for calculating block sums in a matrix (&lt;a
href=&#34;https://leetcode.com/problems/matrix-block-sum/&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/IvanIsCoding/7e0e6cabbf051f0aee0b939a00fbd83b.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I’ll start a line of code and I don’t even know where it’s
going. I just hope I find it along the way. And pray there is no syntax
error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have reached the end of the article, I want to kindly remind
you to read the date of the publication of this article. Happy Aрrіl
Fօօls’ Day! Do not take the content of this post seriously, it is all a
ʝοκе. The contents of this post do not reflect my employer’s opinion on
coding interviews. In fact, they don’t even represent mine.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
